this is the audio on some notes on the
practice of mindfulness of the body I
read a paragraph or so that is relevant
based on venerable aria Vance's
translations that the bio guitar sati so
beginning car 34 there's a bit that says
which is the one thing that should be
developed and in the Buddha answers
mindfulness of the body endowed with
pleasure this is the one thing that
should be developed further in Monaca
119 mmm the Buddha goes on talking about
the mindfulness of the body in relation
to their mindfulness of breathing so he
goes like this
and bickers developed in what way made
much of in what way
his mindfulness of the body of much
fruit of much benefit here because a
bigger gun gone to the forests were gone
to the root of a tree or gone to an
empty heart sits down having crossed his
legs with intention of a straight back
having set up mindfulness in front
that's the important bit mindfulness in
front quite mindfully he breathes in
quite mindfully he breathes out
breathing in long he understands I'm
breathing in long breathing out long he
understands I'm breathing out long so
this is a bit that I wanted to mention a
few points it's he understands based on
the other talks that we gave on
peripheral awareness or awareness done
properly pretty much I wanted to point
out here that when it says here
breathing in long he understands that
he's breathing in long there is not
something that he attends
that is something that he knows so what
he attends it's what's in front and
that's exactly what I said why this is
important before and when I said mindful
and he sets up his mindfulness in front
means he summons his experience as a
whole puts it in front so to speak he
attends to that and while that thing is
enduring and in this case that thing is
breathing he knows what is enduring
without having to attend it as he was
mentioned in in in the essay that I
wrote also called peripheral awareness
people can find it on our website the
knowledge is always peripheral that's
how it works
even if you attend to it you attend to
the particular exemplification of that
but arriving in the knowledge arriving
in the inside arriving in the
understanding of nature of things that's
done at the background of whatever you
attend in other words you cannot through
your pure attention and pure observation
and pure perception arrive at knowledge
knowledge is developed when you
understand the nature of what you're
perceiving attending and so on so that's
why that that's how mindfulness is done
that's why all as again as we've done in
other talks explained peripheral
awareness based on the practice of
mindfulness of the body the referencing
anchoring no matter how you translated
the point is you establish your mind on
the peripheral image while you're
attending something else so you learn
how to not try to attend that which
you're supposed to understand but
instead discern it in regard to whatever
you set up in front of you as your
practice and in this case and also it's
important to know that in this case it's
a person needs to be physically secluded
and you can't do this practice
surrounded by the people no matter how
quiet inside and they are you need
actual physical seclusion physically
removed from the presence of another a
from the presence of another a
phenomenon of another needs to be absent
in your experience you need to be alone
that's why gone to the root of a tree
forest and empty Hut it's not just for
the romantic value once you're in such a
seclusion you sit down you set up
mindfulness to the fore there is no more
specific instruction or you watch the
tip of your nostril and know you bring
the mindfulness to forward and what do
you bring mindfulness sorry of what
mindfulness forward is brought it's
basically of your experience as a whole
experience of breathing that's what
you're doing I'm sitting down and I'm
breathing and you you you you can say
you attend to that just in the general
manner and then while you're doing it
you keep a corner of your eye so to
speak to the knowledge of what you are
doing hence it's quite pointed and
stressed out here breathing in long he
understands I'm breathing in long he
doesn't have to stop breathing or stop
attending mindfulness to the four that
he has brought the attention to the four
in front of him in order to understand
that he is breathing he simply
understands that which he is doing and
he understands it by not trying to and
attend the nature of what he is doing
but by discerning it and that's that's
the entire point I'm making him so
breathing in long he understands he's
breathing long breathing out long he
understands he's breathing out long
breathing in short he understands I am
breathing in short breathing out short
he understands means for any SP he
doesn't mean he has to catch you I mean
out in out it means that at any point of
the duration of in and out breath he
understands the nature of it so this is
the way to describe it that he is fully
aware without attending it directly
because what he but he attends directly
is that which is put in front which is
not the understanding of what he's doing
in front
so then that's how he then start on that
peripheral level including the
phenomenon of this whole body that he
did put in the front initially so he
trains thus I will breed out experience
in the whole body he trains us I will
breed out common the bodily
determinations the body listen car and
again nature of Sankara it's always that
upon which something else depends on
in other words nature Sankara is always
to be in the background the best example
of this is the dependence of nama Rupa
vineya vineya on a nama Rupa as they
will describe it so if you look at nama
Rupa it's held by it's determined by
vijnana if you look even your honor is
it I mean by Navarro which means
determination Sankara is always opposite
of where you look in other words you
cannot see it directly you cannot see it
with with your attention with your
intention because they are already
determined so the point is to recognize
to start developing this indirect vision
of peripheral or indirect revision of
proper mindfulness the only reason I'm
insisting on this description of
peripheral is because well because of
the many misconceptions today people
people do their mindfulness by attending
moment to moment to moment a moment is
absolutely no understanding no buenas of
intentionality developed behind yet it's
actually implicit even in those
misguided acts so he threatened he
trains in a way that he will while he's
breathing in he will be studying these
peripheral body as a determination and
that means exactly that the body that
you eventually learn to discern on the
peripheral level without needing to
directly look at it and start feeling
and touching and getting your sensations
going and so on which is usually how
people practice meditation observing
sensation in this body right in front of
me no you want to discern the body
on the peripheral level because that's
that body because of which you are able
to observe all these sensations and
whatnot right in front of you and that's
why it's said in that anapanasati Sutra
that many translators and scholars get
confused over how to translate it when
it says there is body among bodies that
phenomena stands basically for what your
body is at that present time there is no
other body so that body of breath they
trying to translate or maybe means this
may means body means exactly that means
body discerned peripherally not body
attended directly and there is a
fundamental difference one of them is
object of your attention the other one
is some card of your experience as a
whole and it is that Sankara of the
experience as a whole that the Buddha
talks about as the value of single
mindfulness that you need to develop the
will result in basically full liberation
and supernatural powers or whatever else
if there is an opening for that of
course so that's exactly what this
points out he trains in a way that he
will breathe in discerning these bodily
determinations not looking at the body
not chasing sensations but discerning
that peripheral remote ambiguous image
of the body there and that's also what
it says in satipatthana suta I mentioned
that you know in other talks that where
he where the Buddha says he practices
mindfulness of the body internally
externally and so on
oh he discerns or he prides mindfulness
to the extent necessary for the final
knowledge in relation to he knows the
body is there so he develops mindfulness
of the knowledge the body is there to
the extent necessary for final knowledge
and that's it and it's that body there
is that peripheral image of the body
which we feel attend directly it just
becomes an abstract thought but if you
see it with proper mindfulness with a
corner with indirectly without needing
to attend it then actually it stands for
a phenomenon which is a determination of
your body that you can know right here
in front of that you can see touch
perceive and so on
so then this this this passage goes on
it's saying for one dwelling in this way
vigilant ardent resolute any memories
and thoughts connected with home are
abandoned with abandoning of these
internally and by the way internally is
also something they can almost almost
always there are some exceptions though
but there will be a digression here so
but internally can can almost always be
used to describe that peripheral that
which you cannot directly attend but
your tent becomes external pretty much
even if it's internal things but anyway
let's not get into that here so with the
abandoning of these internally the mind
standstill by discerning this internally
means by surmounting them internally you
abandon them internally the mine
standstill settles down it is unified it
is composed unification composure all
result of proper mindfulness peripheral
anchoring call it whichever way so in
this way because a bigger develops
mindfulness of the body next page then
he goes on furthermore a big walking
understand and walking again while big
who is walking he's aware of the
significance peripheral significance of
his actual act of walking hence he
understand he's walking he's not telling
to himself walking walking touching
touching moving moving feeling feeling
he doesn't need to because all of those
actions are possible to do in a
peripheral level in the first place
because the significance sorry all those
actions are possible to do on the actual
level as in you can attend to them you
can do it like this Soledad because on
the peripheral level a context the
significance of them is already present
and remains present for for as long as
you're doing it it endures
so he understands he's walking or he if
he's standing he understands that he's
standing if he is sitting down he
understands that he's sitting down and
again understanding sitting down means
knowing to sit down doesn't mean
attending the act of sitting down only
person who is not free from doubt would
be needing to attend something to keep
knowing that he's doing but that's not
knowledge and knowledge won't arise from
it that's it that's what I would I would
be describing as a mechanical technique
or a method and it's mechanical because
you assumed almost like a blind faith
though as long as I keep keep looking
keep catching these moments it will
reveal the truth but the truth is in the
knowledge that's why the Buddha talks
about it all the time all if he's lying
down he understands he's lying down or
in whatever way his body is disposed he
understands this for one dwelling in
this way vigilant nod and resolute
memories of thought and thoughts of
connect with Homer abandoned and so on
then he goes on bhiku going forward
going backward he acts with awareness
again awareness results in the
understanding of the peripheral because
of weariness in itself if properly and
could eat in relation well it's anchored
in the peripheral in relation to the
actual awareness is being basically
discerning the relationship between
intention significance and that which
you are attending and signifying to
reacts looking forward looking back he's
one who acts with awareness bending
stretching he's the one who acts with
awareness taking his son Gatti
ball and robe he's the one who acts with
awareness eating drinking consuming
tasting he's the one who acts with
awareness walking standing sitting down
sleeping walking speaking being silent
he's the one who eyes with awareness for
one dwelling in this way vigilant and
resolute any memories and thoughts
connected with home are abandoned with
abandoning of these internal demands
standstill settles down it's unified
it's composed in this way too big too
big to develop my friends to the body
and then goes on the same description
same passage is just
is attending to the repulsive he attends
to it with awareness to turn into the
elements 10 into 9 cemetery
concentration and you could see what's
in common to these things it's common
that they're being attended while
attended he's aware of them he
understands them
he doesn't say he attends to his
understanding of this thing that he
attends and yes the word for attending
here is mana Sakura so that's that's
exactly what we're talking about in
peripheral awareness and what I've been
talking about here so far so tending to
the repulsive he's the one who does that
with awareness awareness and attention
and not the same you could think of if
you struggle understanding this you
could think of awareness being the
background of what you are attending
which means if you try to attend that
background well that's what you're
attending which means your awareness is
the background of that same again and
you can attend that which you perceive
obviously so attending to repulsive a
10-9 cemetery contemplations turn into
the perception of elements obviously so
and then goes on describing the same
thing how to develop Jana's again
according to the following the same
principle furthermore because a big cook
quite secluded from sense desires dwells
having entered upon the first jhana he
makes this very body flow we join
pleasure born of seclusion the image of
the body that has been discerned through
right awareness Oh has been discerned
peripherally he fills it up fully
pervaded if you if you if you rightly
discern and pervade that peripheral body
you're gonna feel it actually because
there is that body as in a we would say
it's doubly present so he makes it flow
all around he fills it up he fully
pervades it so that for him there isn't
anything in the entire body which hasn't
been provided with joy or pleasure and
born seclusion thank if the simile of
the barber then goes to the
first second third for Jonah pretty much
we'll deal the same principle just
replacing one thing with the other
defining so to speak but following the
same peripheral principle that's like is
there beyond mr. de Putte says imagine
109 is there beyond is the more than
this by discerning the same principles
there beyond is the more than this by
discerning the same principle you could
see can you go further and that's how he
would go to the next time in the next
attainment and confirm that there is
more than that and yeah that's another
thing to point out here so through
mindfulness of the body you develop
jhana all through attending to all these
cemetery perceptions and so on
understanding what you are attending
understanding the nature to then you
establish your mind in withdrawal from
sensuality and Parvati body with
pleasure peripherally which then becomes
you Gianna
so the reason I'm mentioning that is
because there is a obviously the most
common notion perception of Buddhist
meditation is you watch in nostrils you
have the experience that's your jhana
but there's absolutely no mention of
that whatsoever
John is sure you can develop Janice on
account of anapanasati and anapanasati
is how we start describing this
understanding your breathing not
attending to the perception of the air
passing through nostrils the results in
your journal when that understanding
becomes established unwavering that's
your jhana and that's exactly why here
it goes on lists all these mindfulness
to the body and then says Janice come on
out of it no mention of any tip of the
nose at the bottom of your belly and so
on so let me just find I think there's
some other interesting passages they are
slightly different but along the same
principle
yeah this one says because it says
because for whoever mindfulness of the
body's developed made much of wherever
he directs his mind to the realization
by discernment of things that can be
realized by discernment right there if
there is an opening he attains the
ability to witness it for himself
imagine because a water jug placed in a
basin full to the brim with water which
crows could drink whenever a strong man
would draw water would water come yes
bhante in just this way because for
whoever mindfulness of the body is
developed again not a special axis
concentration and I don't even know
terminology anymore I stopped following
it but not a specific almost mystical
technique but mindfulness to the body
so however mindfulness of the body is
developed he gets to witness these
discernment of things he gets to if
there is an opening develop even
supernatural powers and that's actually
the passage I'm trying to find here now
but before I get it I can just carry on
so the bhikkhus with mindfulness of the
body frequently developed me much of
made habit of made basis of practice
made familiar thoroughly undertaken
other the felt the first benefit is
there is enduring of non delight and
delight but he does not endure this non
delight he dwells having overcome a
reason on delight there is an enduring
fear and dread but he does not endure
this fear and dread he dwells having
overcome a reason fear and dread this is
actually a very good translation
slightly subtle so let me point it out
there is the enduring fear and dread
which means fear and dread have a reason
on their own
independently of you they have
manifested because that's the nature of
phenomena of Damas to manifest once
manifested they endure that is their
persisting while changing the literal
translation of the Pali term so there is
the enduring fear and dread but the man
who is developed among who is developed
mindfulness is worried he does not enjoy
that he doesn't own that endurance that
endurance does not affect him does not
pertain to him it's not his it's on his
problem thus he doesn't endure the
endurance of fear and dread the
endurance of non delight the endurance
of discomfort the enteral the endurance
of had a hardship slander gossip
piercing evil displeasing world's
disagreeable insult all that all those
things arise they endure on their own
having endured they've ceased having
India they've ceased but the monk who
has developed a month of all he does not
endure it he dwells all in having
overcome there isn't fear and dread
there is patience though it's cold heat
hung the first contact with flies
mosquitoes when heat creepy-crawlies
that's an interesting there is endurance
with a bad speech unwholesome ways of
speaking and there is a reason feelings
in the body they're painful sharp rough
severe disagreeable displeasing taking
away life then carries on the one who
develops mindfulness of the body makes
much of it properly discerns the the
phenomenon of the body there very
thoroughly he is the one who obtains at
will without trouble without difficulty
the four Gianna's of the higher mind
Pleasant dwellings here and now based on
understanding of the nature of the body
not based on a meditation to
contemporary meditation technique he
experiences the various kinds of powers
again all of this is based on the
mindfulness of the body like extending
your arm sitting down talking not trying
to attend to it but actually
understanding the nature of it he
experienced the very various kinds of
powers having been one he's many having
been many
he exerts control over his body as far
as the Brahma world with the divine air
element which is clarified and surrounds
the human he his sounds both divine and
human by the far near he understands the
minds of other beings of other
individuals having encompassed them by
mind he understands the mind with passion as
he understands the mind with passion as
mind with passion he understands mind
free from passion as mind free from
passion her mind will yell will has mind
free from your will or mind with
delusion of mind free from delusion so
he understands all of this he discerns
it he understands unliberated mind has
unliberated liberated as liberated
eighth benefit is he recollects various
formulas that is one bath tubas with
such a reason with such an explanation
he recollects various kinds of formal
lives why because even the memory that's how
why because even the memory that's how
memory works it's the it's the extent of
the peripheral extent of non direct so
you get reminded to attending something
gets you remind you peripherally so if
you develop the mind in regard to the
mindfulness peripherally it can go as
far as to start remembering previous
lives what was before these perceptions
before the the perception of this life
that unifies all these particular
perceptions because again it's the same
relationship same principle the ninth
benefit is with the divine higher
element which is clarified and sermons
the human he sees beings passing away he
reappearing inferior excellent beautiful
ugly good destination by destination he
understands that being beings go
according to directions and the tenth
benefit is having realized for himself
by recognizing here and now the
liberation of the mind liberation of
understanding he dwells having entered
upon the destruction of the art flows
which is without art flows so because we
mindfulness of the body frequently
development much of may the habit of
made a basis of practice made familiar
and taken understood these are the 10
benefits to be expected
okay well let me I can read them I
haven't read these passages now the next
ones but you just go ahead I can read it
in will see if I have something to say
about anybody I'm sure they're
interesting so this is a good Randy
Carnell I think book of ones 575 to 627 so
I think book of ones 575 to 627 so
various verses from 563 and so on so one
one thing because developed made much of
leads to great existential angst leading
to great benefit leads to great safety
from bondage leads to mindfulness and
awareness leads to attainment of knowing
and seeing leads to pleasant dwelling in
this very life leads to realization of
the fruit of wisdom and liberation which
one thing it's the mindfulness of the
body this one thing because developed me
much of leads to great existential
anxiety leads to great benefit leads to
great safety from bondage leads to
mindfulness in awareness leads to the
attainment of knowing and seeing leads
to pleasant welling in this very life
leads to liberation
well I'm sure that whoever listens to
this would want to know how does that
make sense then it leads to great
extension anxiety then leads to great
benefit actually it's a very good
translation again that's why I chose
whenever I want so papers that I got
yeah some some way guys somewhat arty Oh Riko
some some way guys somewhat arty Oh Riko
yeah so what it leads to extension
anxiety because that's the first step
basically that's the first step to to
liberation you could say that
acknowledging the existence inside and
you don't have to take my word for it
you can find any suitor that the Buddha
talks about a young man realizing that
he subject to suffering and so on and
there is always the language says he
realized that he's prey to suffering so
if you like that's obviously that's
something that everyone
would often read all that oh yeah prey
to suffering sure but if you stop and
think about it reflect on how would you
feel if you're being hunted not by this
person or that but by nature of
suffering how would you feel if you
recognize that your human situation can
be pounced upon by any suffering from
any direction and you can't even foresee
it let alone do something about it so
imagine if you're in the middle of the
wilderness there is a wild beast there
they can kill you and you can't see it
you can't hear it you can only know you
work you start knowing you start
basically recognizing that you are its
prey that it can jump on you at any time
and that's it it will well if he doesn't
kill you it will harm you and eventually
of course you will die so and how would
you feel you did like full of dread and
anxiety overwhelming one as well and the
Buddha would always say that that would
be like a prerequisite for a young man
to leave the household life and go and
seek the truth but again people would
over read like often read over it
because yeah I mean it's just ah ok
prayed to suffering sure yeah we were
also suffering but no you actually had
to acknowledge it and feel it he feels
he's prey to suffering he feels
suffering is that hunter and yeah that's
not something that's not hot like
subject to feeling suffering is
something you cannot even conceive how
would you prevent it no amount of effort
actually can make any difference
fundamentally even if you live
completely shelter life because
suffering arises internally any of your
efforts are efforts directed towards the
external so that's exactly how if you
start being mindful of your body you
start being mindful of the perilous
situation of being a living human
subjected to elements accidents will of
others things out of your control all of
those bases for anxiety so you start
practicing mindfulness correct
you start discerning the the notion of
the body your body being there in the
world you started selling that
peripheral you start understanding it
you're gonna be filled with existential
anxiety and that's just inevitable now
how much you're gonna suffer on account
of that existential anxiety
well that's determining how much of your
mind has been developed how much of your
mind but basically how much pain you can
take I remember reading that a long time
ago I was a big quenya on aji rocoto
Yugoslavia monk who obviously was the
the whose books inspire me it was the
the tera vaada and even he kind of
understood this I mean he was often sort
of frou-frou contemporary approach but
he was a philosopher before and so
there's only so much he was able to
ignore so he understood that that he
said he said him won one of his books
that the type of suffering that is
necessary to acknowledge and start to
feel in order to practice the Buddhist
teaching correctly is the type of
suffering that for most people would
probably result in some form of mental
derangement neurosis psychosis or
something as in they won't be able to
hold they won't be able to handle it so
you have to be able to handle it if you
can't handle existential anxiety without
breaking down without without sort of
doing something uncontrollable you won't
be able to then develop it further into
liberation that's where people when they
would back in the day when the Buddha
would ascribe on Nibbana is they would
freak out fall on the ground start
ripping their hair out yes that's a
genuine description of a terror because
for them Nibbana
is death so for particular Nibbana is
death basically for what he thinks that
is better so well to adhere in order to
be able to deal with existential anxiety
you have to be established in virtue so
the reason why people don't have enough
mental strength to cope with the reason
intentioned read an extension Santi is
because their behavior hasn't been purified
their behavior hasn't been purified
beforehand as the Buddha would say so
for somebody who started taking the
virtue seriously the precepts seriously
they restraint seriously watching the
speech practicing non harm no neo will
and definitely non sensuality yeah that
is how you develop the mind so it can
take the pain any any principle of
strength you develop strength by
exposing your weakness by challenging it
bit by bit by bit and the mind adapts
the body adapts that's how you become
stronger so if the virtue has been
developed beforehand mindfulness to the
body will reveal the great existential
anxiety mahoto some vague ayah somewhat Otte it
mahoto some vague ayah somewhat Otte it
will reveal the great existential
anxiety that you will be able to hold
and if you are able to hold it then that
mindfulness of the body leads to the
next thing which is the great benefit
great safety from bondage leads to
mindfulness and awareness leads the
payment of knowledge Pleasant dwelling
in this very life to freedom to our own
ship but not if you ignore it not if you
know the extension anxiety so yeah that
is indeed an interesting suta although
I'm sure if you find other English
translations they're going to be very
different but that's just the nature of
the suitors their sojourn and also
condensed in the meaning that even if
you read pure Pali you're going to be
putting your own views so you want to be
honest and you want to look for a
context of your understanding that can
then remain unchanged regardless of the
suitor you reading you want to basically
this star discerning the nature the
principles then no amount of suitor or
rather if it's challenged by different
suitors means it's not adequate
principle you can't just having a patchwork and
you can't just having a patchwork and
just patching it as it arises modifying
it you want one suitor to
present the old suitors inside into one
the nature one suta means you are able
to understand all the other suitors if
you potentially if you read them if you
if you sort of discerned it and that's
from that point of view it will also
become clear how it is possible to how
it was possible to become an art hand
simply by one discussed by the Buddha or
even part of it yeah because one
contains the whole nature the whole
universal principle of the Dhamma and
again that's what the Buddha said
himself so I think there's probably be
enough for now
there are quite a few more passages but
I could perhaps do a part two or three
because I think even this is more than
enough for people to follow